The idea of experience replay and its application to training
经验回放和使用它来训练
neural networks for reinforcement learning isn't new.
强化学习神经网络并不是什么新的理念
It was originally proposed to make more efficient use of observed experiences.
它一开始用于更高效地使用观察的经验
Consider the basic online Q-learning algorithm where we
对于基本的在线 Q 学习算法
interact with the environment and at each time step,
我们与环境进行互动并且在每个时间步
we obtain a state action reward next state tuple.
获得一个动作 状态 奖励 下个状态元组
Learn from it and then discarded.
从中学习规律 然后丢弃
Moving on to the next tuple in the following timestep.
在下个时间步移到下个元组
This seems a little wasteful.
似乎有点浪费
We could possibly learn more from these experienced tuples if we stored them somewhere.
如果我们将这些经验元组存储在某个地方 我们可能会从中学习更多规律
Moreover, some states are pretty rare to come by and some actions can be pretty costly,
此外 某些状态很罕见 某些动作的代价很高
so it would be nice to recall such experiences.
因此最好能够回顾这些经验
That is exactly what a replay buffer allows us to do.
这正是回放缓冲区的作用
We store each experienced tuple in this buffer as we are interacting with
当我们与环境互动时 我们将每个经验元组存储在这个缓冲区中
the environment and then sample a small batch of tuples from it in order to learn.
然后从中抽取一小批元组以进行学习
As a result, we are able to learn from individual tuples multiple times,
因此 我们能够从单个元组中多次学习规律
recall rare occurrences, and in general make better use of fire experience.
回顾罕见的状态并更充分地利用经验
But there is another critical problem that experience replay can
经验回放还能够解决另一个关键问题
help with and this is what DQN takes advantage of.
这正是 DQN 所利用的方面
If you think about the experiences being obtained,
如果你思考获得的经验
you realize that every action AT affects the next state ST in some way,
就会发现每个动作 AT 都以某种方式影响下个状态 ST
which means that a sequence of experienced tuples can be highly correlated.
意味着一系列经验元组可能关系非常紧密
A naive Q-learning approach that learns from each of these experiences in
按顺序从这些经验中学习规律的简单 Q 学习方法
sequential order runs the risk of getting swayed by the effects of this correlation.
面临受到这种联系影响的风险
With experience replay, can sample from this buffer at random.
借助经验回放 我们可以随机地从缓冲区中取样
It doesn't have to be in the same sequence as we stored the tuples.
不一定必须是存储元组的同一顺序
This helps break the correlation and ultimately prevents
这有助于打破相互之间的联系
action values from oscillating or diverging catastrophically.
并最终防止动作值严重振动或发散
Now, this might be a little hard to understand,
理解起来可能有点困难
so let's look at an example.
我们来看一个示例
I'm learning to play tennis and I like to practice rallying against the wall.
我正在学习打网球并对着墙壁不断练习
I'm more confident with my forehand shot than my backhand,
我更擅长于正手击球 而不是反手击球
and I can hit the ball fairly straight.
我可以比较直地击中墙壁
So the ball keeps coming back around the same area
因此球不断回到位于右手边的同一区域
to my right and I keep hitting forehand shots.
我可以不断正手击球
Now, if I were an online Q-learning agent learning as I play,
如果我是一个在线 Q 学习智能体 学习如何玩网球
this is what I might pick up.
我可能会学会以下规律
When the ball comes to my right,
当球朝着我的右侧飞来时
I should hit with my forehand,
我应该用正手击球
less certainly at first but with increasing confidence as I repeatedly hit the ball.
一开始不太确定 但是当我不断练习击球时 越来越自信可以这么操作
Great! I'm learning to play forehand pretty well,
很棒！我的正手击球技巧很厉害
but I'm not exploring the rest of the state space.
但是我没有探索剩下的状态空间
This could be addressed by using
解决方法是使用 Epsilon 贪婪策略
an Epsilon-Greedy policy acting randomly with a small chance.
以很小的概率随机采取动作
So I try different combinations of states and actions and sometimes I make mistakes,
我会尝试不同的状态和动作组合 有时候会出错
but I eventually figure out the best overall policy.
但是我最终会得出最佳整体策略
Use a forehand shot when the ball comes to
当球朝着我的右侧飞来时 用正手击球
my right and a backhand when it comes to my left.
朝着我的左侧飞来时 使用反手
Perfect, this learning strategy seems to work well with a Q-table,
很棒 这个学习策略似乎很适合 Q 表格
where we have assumed this highly simplified state space with just two discrete states.
我们认为这个非常简单的状态空间只有两个离散状态
But when we consider a continuous state space things can fall apart. Let's see how.
但是对于连续状态空间 情况会变得很糟糕 我们来看看
First the ball can actually come anywhere between the extreme left and extreme right.
首先 球可以从最左端和最右端之间的任何方向飞来
If I tried to discretize this range into
如果我尝试将这个范围
small buckets I wouldn't have too many possibilities.
离散化为很小的分桶 则会有太多可能性
What if I end up learning a policy with holes in it,
如果我学习的策略存在漏洞呢
states or situations that I may not have visited during practice.
我在练习时可能没有遇到一些状态或情况
Instead it makes more sense to use a function approximator like a linear combination of
相反 使用函数逼近器会更合适
RBF kernels or a Q-network that can generalize my learning across the space.
例如线性组合径向基函数核或 Q 网络 它们可以泛化空间内的学习效果
Now, every time the ball comes to my right and I successfully hit a forehand shot,
现在 每次球飞向右侧时 我成功地用正手击中
my value function changes slightly.
值函数稍微发生了变化
It becomes more positive around the exact region where the ball came,
它对球的精确区域更加确定
but also raises the value for the forehand shot in general across the state space.
但是也提高了整个状态空间内的正手击球值
The effect is less pronounced away from the exact spot,
效果是偏离精确位置的幅度越来越小
but over time it can add up.
但是会逐渐累积起来
And that's exactly what happens when I try to learn while playing,
这正是在玩球时尝试学习所发生的情况
processing each experience tuple in order.
即按顺序处理每个经验元组
For instance, if my forehand shot is fairly straight,
例如 如果正手击球很直
I likely get back the ball around the same spot.
我很可能会在同一位置遇到球
This produces a state very similar to the previous one,
这样会生成一个与上个状态非常相似的状态
so I use my forehand again and if it is successful
因此我再次使用正手 如果成功了
it reinforces my belief that forehand is a good choice.
则增加了我认为正手很合适的信念
I can easily get trapped in this cycle.
我很容易陷入这种循环中
Ultimately, if I don't see too many examples of the ball coming to my left for a while,
最终 如果一段时间内没有见到太多朝着左侧飞来的球
then the value of the forehand shot can become greater
那么在整个状态空间内 正手击球的值
than backhand across the entire state space.
比反手击球的值更大
My policy would then be to choose forehand regardless of where I see the ball coming.
我的策略变成无论看到球朝着哪个方向飞来 我都选择正手
Disaster. Okay, how can we fix this?
太糟糕 如何解决这一问题？
The first thing I should do is stop learning while practicing.
首先是停止一边练习一边学习
This time is best spent in trying out different shots
这时候最适合尝试不同的击球方式
playing a little randomly and thus exploring the state space.
随机地击球并探索状态空间
It then becomes important to remember my interactions,
然后必须记住我的互动
what shots worked well in what situations, et cetera.
在哪些情形下哪些击球方式效果很好 等等
When I take a break or when I am back home and resting,
当我短暂休息或回家休息的时候
that's a good time to recall these experiences and learn from them.
最适合回忆这些经验并从中学习规律
The main advantage is that now I have a more comprehensive set of examples.
主要优势是现在拥有一个更全面的示例集合
Somewhere the ball came to my right,
有时候球朝着右侧飞来
somewhere it came to my left,
有时候朝着左侧飞来
some forehand shots, some backhand.
有时候正手击球 有时候反手击球
I can generalize patterns from across these examples,
我可以通过这些示例总结规律
recalling them in whatever order I please.
按照任何顺序回顾它们
This helps me avoid being fixated on one region of
这样可以避免固定在一个状态空间区域
the state space or reinforcing the same action over and over.
或不断加强相同的动作
After a round of learning,
在一轮学习之后
I can go back to playing with my updated value function.
我可以使用更新的值函数继续玩球
Again, collect a bunch of experiences and then learn from them in a batch.
再次收集一系列的经验并批量学习
In this way, experience replay can help us learn a more robust policy,
这样 经验回放可以帮助我们学习更鲁棒的策略
one that is not affected by the inherent correlation
这种策略不会受到一系列观察经验元组
present in the sequence of observed experience tuples.
之间的固有联系的影响
If you think about it,
仔细思考就会发现
this approach is basically building a database of
这种方法基本上是构建一个样本数据库
samples and then learning a mapping from them.
然后从中学习映射
In that sense experience replay helps us reduce
这样的话 经验回放可以帮助我们
the reinforcement learning problem or at least value
将强化学习问题（或至少值学习部分）
learning portion of it to a supervised learning scenario.
简化为监督学习情形
That's clever.
这很机智
We can then apply other models learning techniques and
然后 我们可以将在监督学习环境中
best practices developed in
开发的学习技巧和最佳做法
the supervised learning literature through reinforcement learning.
应用到强化学习中
We can even improve upon this idea, for example,
甚至可以完善这一理念
by prioritizing experience tuples that are rare or more important.
例如 使罕见或更重要的经验元组优先级更高